Guide to the Joseph Jastrow papers, 1875-1961 and undated RL.10121
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joseph Jastrow papers
1875-1961 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jastrow, Joseph, 1863-1944
RL.10121
6.5 Linear Feet 12 boxes approximately 1,015 items
Collection contains correspondence; lectures, speeches, prose, and poetry; published articles; book reviews; photographs and negatives; a scrapbook; and newspaper clippings. Subjects include the Jastrow family of Philadelphia and the Szold family of Baltimore, early psychology and psychophysics, the University of Wisconsin at Madison, Jewish society and Judaism in Baltimore and Philadelphia, and the Zionist movement. Correspondents include his father, Talmudic scholar Marcus Jastrow, and sister-in-law and U.S. Zionist movement leader, Henrietta Szold. Papers also include information on Joseph Jastrow's adopted son, Benjamin (Benno) Jastrow; a typed memoir, circa 1920, by Benno's biological father contains a moving account of the tragic outcome of the Spanish influenza epidemic (1918-1919), which led to the adoption of the infant Benno by the Jastrow family. Glass plates in the collection contain charts of symbols which may be results of experiments in involuntary hand movements, traced by his invention, the "automograph."
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, glass plate negatives are closed to general use. Viewing copies may need to be made for access to content. Other access only with permission of Rubenstein staff.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical Note
Polish-born Joseph Jastrow (1863-1944), was a psychologist and professor at the University of Wisconsin. He was one of the founding members of the American Society for Psychical Research, and was a pioneer in the field of psychology, specializing in optical illusions, the psychology of the blind, and parapsychology, and brought his research to public attention through lectures and popular culture magazines. He was married to Rachel (Szold) Jastrow.
Provenance
The Joseph Jastrow Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1959.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm copy available.
Collection Overview
This collection contains the papers of Joseph Jastrow (1863-1944), a scholar and writer pioneering in the field of psychology, most of his career spent at the University of Wisconsin. It includes correspondence of Jastrow and his wife, Rachel (Szold) Jastrow, with their families, principally concerning family matters, but with references to affairs of the University of Wisconsin; Judaism in Baltimore, Maryland, and Madison, Wisconsin; and the Zionist movement.
Also included are photographs of the Szold and Jastrow families, and a set of glass plate negatives with charts of symbols, perhaps showing the results of experiments in involuntary hand movements, traced by his invention, the "automograph." psychology experiments.
There are manuscripts of Jastrow's lectures, speeches, prose and poetry; galley proofs of several articles; a diary kept during a vacation in Spain; a scrapbook containing copies of his articles and book reviews; a compilation of his early writings; copies of his articles in pamphlet form; and newspaper clippings.
Personal papers also include information on Joseph Jastrow's adopted son, Benjamin (Benno) Jastrow; a typed memoir, circa 1920, by Benno's biological father contains a moving account of the tragic outcome of the Spanish influenza epidemic (1918-1919), which led to the adoption of the infant Benno by the Jastrow family.
College teachers -- United States -- Correspondence; Influenza Epidemic, 1918-1919 -- Personal narratives; College teachers as authors; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Jews -- Maryland -- Baltimore; Optical illusions -- Psychological aspects; Parapsychology -- Study and teaching -- United States; Psychology -- Study and teaching -- United States; Psychology, experimental -- Study and teaching -- United States; Zionism and Judaism; Madison (Wis.) -- Social life and customs; Baltimore (Md.) -- Social life and customs; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Social life and customs; Glass plate negatives; Photographs; Szold, Henrietta, 1860-1945; Szold family; Jastrow, Marcus, 1829-1903; Jastrow family; University of Wisconsin--Madison
- Joseph Jastrow papers, 1875-1961
  - Letters, 1875-1889; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1890-1894; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1895-1908; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Letters, 1909-1945 and undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Volumes, undated (Box 5)
  - Volumes, undated (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1887-1907 (Box 7)
  - Printed material, undated; 1 folders (Box 8)
  - Photographs, chiefly 20th century, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Photographs, chiefly 20th century, 16 folders (Box 10)
  - Family-related papers and printed material, circa 1920-1960s (Box 11)
    Material Details
    Includes memorabilia regarding Jastrow's sister-in-law, Henrietta Szold, and his son, Benjamin (Benno) Jastrow, who was adopted by Joseph Jastrow and his wife. A typed memoir by Benno's biological father, several pages long, gives a moving account of his family's struggle to overcome the consequences of the Spanish Influenza epidemic, in which his wife died, and the adoption of the infant Benno by the Jastrows.
  - Glass plate negatives, 1890s?, 10 plates (Box 12)
    Scope and Contents
    Glass plates have been housed in sink mats.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original negative glas plates are closed to general use; viewing copies may need to be made for access to content. Direct access only by permission of Rubenstein Library staff. Please contact the library before coming to use this material.